A Guide to the John Terry Chase Manuscript Papers on "Gum Springs: The Triumph of a Black Community", 1987-1989
Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library
The John Terry Chase Manuscript Papers on "Gum Springs: The Triumph of a Black Community", 1987-1989
Fairfax County Public Library
MSS 08-22
.63 linear feet
The John Terry Chase Manuscript Papers on Gum Springs: The Triumph of a Black Community (1990) consists of .63 linear feet and spans the years 1987-1989 and contains copies of primary and secondary historical documents, author’s notes, and manuscript drafts. Subjects covered are the Gum Springs neighborhood in Fairfax County, Virginia; Gum Springs’ founder West Ford; the relationship between Gum Springs and Mount Vernon; African-American history; and race relations.
Chase, John Terry (1934-2014)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None
Acquisition Information
Unknown
Historical and Biographical Information
John Terry Chase was born on November 7, 1934 in Deerfield, Massachusetts. He graduated from Reed College in 1959 with a BA in History and later received an MA in History from George Mason University in 1987.
After relocating to Arlington, Virginia, Chase served as a speech writer for the Environmental Protection Agency during the Carter Administration. He later taught American history at the International School in Bethesda, Maryland from 1989 to 1995.
He authored a number of history books, including "Gum Springs: Triumph of a Black Community" (1990), which was commissioned by the Heritage Resources Branch of the Fairfax County Office of Comprehensive Planning. The book focused on the dynamics of community building and history in Gum Springs. The community earned its name from a gum tree on the property that George Washington’s nephew, Bushrod, willed to freedman West Ford.
Chase also wrote "The Study of American History: Volume 1" (1974) and "Recreation for Urban America" (1979) with the National Committee for Urban Recreation. In addition, he and his wife Sara Lee Hannum Chase co-edited two anthologies of contemporary and nature-related poetry: "To Play Man Number One: Poems of Modern Man" (1969) and "The Wind is Round" (1970).
Chase died of a stroke at age 79 on June 1, 2014 at a retirement community in Mitchellville, Maryland.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Gum Springs, Virginia Collection - MSS 03-10
None
Index Terms
African-American History; Chase, John Terry; Ford, West; Gum Springs neighborhood in Fairfax County, Virginia; Gum Springs and Mount Vernon; Race Relations
Container List
- Gum Springs - Ch. 1 1653-1833, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Gum Springs - Ch. 2, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Gum Springs - Ch. 3, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Gum Springs - Ch. 4, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Gum Springs - Ch. 5, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Gum Springs - Ch. 6, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Gum Springs - Documentation, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Gum Springs - Illustrations, T. Chase, 1987, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Gum Springs - Manuscript Draft, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Gum Springs - Manuscript Draft, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Gum Springs - Manuscript Draft (with payment request), 1987, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Gum Springs - Manuscript Draft, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 12)